thank you
[Music]
good evening good day and welcome to the
150th episode of the Oscar music show uh
it's incredible we have reached episode
150 it's all thanks to you all without
your viewership without your support we
would never have been here I would have
stopped after two three episodes if
nobody was watching so this is all
thanks to you I am very grateful thank
you so much I really appreciate it and
obviously we will keep going yep
um so yeah let's uh before we do
anything else let's see who all is there
on the live chat I can see lots of
people I can see kitten Chopra
the god of alpha harsh Dubai just a
guide
because Hirohito
foreign
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you wherever you are
welcome to the live stream
so let us now with that said get into
the questions what shall we eat what
shall we take first okay let's take the
obvious question first lots of people
have asked me this question and it is a
question about my about our friend Mr
vir Das
and your take on that an Indian says
your reply to vir Das at TRS calling
your brown Kohli comment racist Divya
says uh radio
watches response to what you said in one
week's show it was hilarious playing
with Tim card and all that
yes I did happen to watch that I haven't
watched the entire podcast I've seen the
clip in which he supposedly responds to
my criticism of him on the same podcast
the PRS show so a few months ago I've
done as you know many podcasts with
ranveer so a few months ago he had asked
me ranveer on his podcast about my views
my opinion about what about vir das's
actions abroad the things he said about
India on on foreign soil and all that
and I I had essentially criticized him
uh I don't remember exactly what I said
I haven't watched that clip again it's
been too so long but apparently I called
him a brown [\h__\h] yeah and and uh so
virdas uh so ranveer in this clip that I
saw a couple of days ago he asks viridas
to respond to my criticism and virida
says that uh me calling him a brown
[\h__\h] is is racist apparently yeah
so so me calling vir Das a brown [\h__\h]
is apparently racist
before I even address that it's
perfectly fine for vir Das to to make
all kinds of anti-india anti-hindu
statements it's fine for him to call all
Indian men rapists that's not offensive
but me calling [\h__\h] is offensive he
gets upset what sort of what sort of
logic is this I mean that's hypocrisy
now when it comes to him saying that uh
me calling him a brown [\h__\h] is a
racist
is it even possible to be racist against
someone of your own ethnicity
I mean vir Das is Indian I am Indian we
are the same people we are the same
ethnicity
we have essentially the same Heritage
same past same ancestry how can I be
racist to my own ethnicity is it even
possible yeah and maybe he has uh maybe
he has taken issue to this word [\h__\h]
yeah and maybe the term [\h__\h] is
apparently racist in his mind so virdas
is attempting to construct a career in
the United States he must be very uh
aware of U.S culture is he aware of
something called the rap industry the
rap rap music industry in the US it is
dominated by African-American people
yeah all these rap
Stars yeah Coolio and LL Cool J I don't
know there must be many more these days
I'm not really keeping track of it now
in the U.S rap industry and and VIR the
says that me using the word Cooley
against him is like using the N word
again for against a in African-American
person black person
so he's equating [\h__\h] with the n-word
in the U.S rap industry
if you listen to the rap music they use
the N word all the time
in the U.S it is perfectly acceptable
for a black person to use the n-word
for it is used sometimes as a term of
endearment among black people sometimes
in other other ways as well yeah but
it's perfectly acceptable for black
people to use and and word it is
completely unacceptable for a white
person to use the N word because of the
history because the white people
invented this world this word and they
have used it for for centuries in a
dedicatory way
you know racist way against black people
so for a white person to use the n-word
is completely unacceptable black people
use it all the time that's how it is
that's the social convention similarly
among Indians
the same way if a white person were to
use the word [\h__\h] for an Indian or for
a Chinese person or a Japanese person or
an Eastern Asian person that would be
racism but an Indian person using the
word [\h__\h] is obviously not racism you
can't be racist against yourself so this
is a rather ridiculous
thing that avirdas said he is trying to
to portray himself as a victim here yeah
and if the word [\h__\h] is apparently
racist in his mind then what is this
exactly
the 1983 movie Cooley starring one of
bollywood's great Superstars Amitabh
Bachchan is this a racist movie or maybe
it's an old movie from 1983 maybe times
have changed yeah then what about this
movie [\h__\h] number one with some
Bollywood people who I don't really know
this is a very recent movie [\h__\h]
number one is this also a racist movie
virudas
what sort of logic do people come up
with how is the term coolly racist when
an Indian person uses it yeah if a white
person calls an Indian racist or a
Chinese racist or a Japanese person or
anybody else racist calls them Cooley if
a white person uses the word [\h__\h]
that's racism an Indian person using the
word [\h__\h] is not racism now let's
understand some people would say that uh
I use the term [\h__\h] out of anger or
out of emotion well that's not the case
yeah
is a person who carries heavy loads yes
typically these are the porters you will
see at Railway stations historically
that they've been used uh you know you
have these Porters who would uh carry
heavy weights on Railway stations and
they were called coolies yeah
historically so akuli is a person
who carries
heavy loads that's what a [\h__\h] is
now uh
so I use the term [\h__\h] as in in the
sense of a brown man virdas carrying The
White Man's Burden
you may have heard of the poem White
Man's Burden which was written by the
very racist uh indian-born uh British
poet Rudyard Kipling The White Man's
Burden and in this poem he depicts the
he says that the white people are their
responsibility is to civilize the
non-white people because non-white
people are backward primitive all that
barbaric yeah and the white people are
civilized so it is The White Man's
Burden to civilize the non-white people
the brown people the black people and so
on so forth the Eastern Asian people the
Indians and all that so
even today these racist uh
tropes these racist attitudes still
continue so today you will see in the
West in the U.S in in the UK they their
Publications like the guardian the New
York Times the New York Post The
Washington Post and so on so forth they
have they carry these very strongly
anti-india articles but they always they
usually employ Indian origin people to
write these things very racist very
patronizing very derogatory articles
about India and it's usually Indian
origin people who are made to write
these articles so that they can keep
their they can say that we didn't write
it it's an Indian origin person to write
it or and who wrote it our hands are
clean so today it's perfectly acceptable
to be racist against Indians in in the
west and especially against Hindus yeah
but not against certain other religions
so racism is acceptable against Indians
and against Hindus in a certain way and
they typically employ Indian origin
people to write these derokee articles
that means that they are making the in
Indians Indian origin people the brown
people to carry The White Man's Burden
and they can say that our hands are
clean so vir Das is one of those brown
coolies he is carrying the White Man's
Burden yeah in the sense that he's going
outside of India he is performing as
apparently as a comic in the U.S and
other places I I believe I don't know
and he is you know ridiculing India he's
making fun of India he's criticizing
India uh so that is what I meant by
virdas being a brown [\h__\h] he is
carrying the White Man's Burden on
behalf of his of the people
who he wishes to please yeah because he
wants to create a career in the U.S and
uh obviously he's not a very funny guy
he's rather unfunny but yeah he serves
the purpose he serves the purpose of
carrying The White Man's Burden so
that's what I meant
by calling virdas a brown [\h__\h] and I
stand by it it is not racist in any way
whatsoever his contention that I was
being racist against him is reasonable
it is asinine it is laughable it's
ridiculous yes no
the thing is virdas did he address my
criticism
in his uh
when the ranveer invited him to do so I
don't think he was able to address my
criticism at all my criticism was why
did you criticize India abroad why did
you make fun of India abroad why did you
ridicule India abroad
you know it's it's uh
you will never see
an American person coming to India and
then ridiculing their country
you will never see a Chinese person
coming to India and really cooling their
country you will never see a person from
the UK coming to India and ridiculing
the UK you will never see a French
person coming to India in ridiculing
France but you will see lots of Indians
these Brown coolies who go to the west
and attempt to ingratiate themselves
over there by
criticizing India ridiculing India
making fun of India saying whatever
these people want you to say yeah
you know if you really care for India
you know in Friendship how it is when
two people are real genuine friends and
one person needs to be criticized that
criticism is done in private it's never
done in public when you have a small
child and the child is is maybe you know
needs some improvement you do the
criticism of the child in private you
don't do it in public
yeah so if virdas really cares about
India and he thinks India needs to
change and India needs to improve he
could have said these things in India
but no he chose to go half half the
planet away the other side of the planet
and make fun of India in the U.S and my
question was why did he do that he has
not answered the question he has no
answers you know virdas is very brave
to speak about India abroad he's he has
very bravely criticized India abroad
made fun of India abroad he has very
bravely ridiculed India abroad yeah
yeah and and you think that's bravery
there are no consequences for for
ridiculing India there are no adverse
consequences for ridiculing Hinduism
there are consequences for ridiculing
certain other religions in some other
countries but he won't do that you know
so he comes to runway's show or rinbase
gives gives him the opportunity to
address this and he essentially plays
the victim card yeah he's making fun of
India over there and all that now I
would like to invite vir Das
to uh well if he wants to he can do this
you know he speaks about two Indians
well I would like to uh
tell virdas that there are two Americas
also there are two Americas
yeah there is one America that he wishes
to live in the wonderful America that he
wants to be a part of but there is a
second America an America that
conducted the genocide of at least 56
million Native Americans well we'll thus
speak about that there is a second
America where which has the history of
horrific racism against black people and
non-white people which still continues
racial profiling
killing killing by cop and so much more
will virda speak about this there is a
second America whose pharmaceutical
industry exploits its own people it it's
all coming out these days will Vedas
speak about that second America there is
a second America where homelessness is
rampant where gun crime is rampant drug
abuse child abuse sexual abuses is
rampant will virda speak about that
there is an America where California is
is has descended into hell-like status
there is no rule of law and order there
is there are people doing drugs on the
street there are people
clapping on the streets there are people
living on the streets the homelessness
it's terrible and there is no rule of
law will virda speak about that there is
a city called Chicago in the U.S where
there are more crimes and grapes in a
weekend than you have in India in in in
Delhi or Mumbai over a month
will we thus speak about that
will be the speak about the U.S the
second America
which killed 2 million Iraqis innocent
men women children you know innocent
people
in their invasion of Iraq you know
directly or indirectly the shock and no
campaign
which which blasted which flattened
cities and killed everyone within will
we will not speak about that there is
the second America which is still right
now as you speak carrying out a war by
proxy in Yemen and killing civilians
will we will not speak about that there
is a second America
which tested two nuclear weapons on
Japanese civilians in 1945. and this
second America has been occupying Japan
militarily against the will of its
citizens since 1945 it's still happening
today will will thus speak about that
so I'm inviting virdas to to you know to
be balanced you spoke about two Indians
why don't you go and speak about two
Americas and speak about that in the U.S
let's see if you can do that he will not
do it because it's a coward
if he does that if vir Das does that his
precious little Visa will be torn up his
hopes of a green card and future
citizenship will evaporate and he will
be he will have to come back to India
and he will have to entertain Indians
with his
comedy his non-existent comedy that's
the problem
so that is my if you if you want a
response to to vir that this is that's
my response to be with us if you dare
speak about two Americas go ahead
brother brother go for it yeah I I
invite you to do that let's see if you
can speak about two Americas in the US
or even in India come to Indians
recorded let's see if you do that yep
so that's what I have to say about this
and and I also saw that lots of people
lots of people are criticizing ranveer
uh please don't do that why what's the
need what's so what's the reason for
that if ranveer had not invited vir Das
on his podcast you would not have seen
viridas's response yes so please don't
criticize ranveer and whatever else yeah
I really appreciate the fact that
ranveer for inviting Vedas and giving
him the opportunity to give his
non-response to my criticism all right
so yeah there it goes uh that's my
response to this entire thing I I hope
the matter rests here and let's see if
virus goes ahead and speaks about two
Americas the way he was so bravely happy
to speak about to India's yeah let's see
if he does that
all right
okay second question is uh yeah lots of
people have asked me about this as well
so harsh says the government is planning
to open Yale Oxford Etc foreign
universities in India is it good or will
it destroyable Society more so foreign
branch in branches in India of foreign
universities and the geopolitical
debases the government of India plans to
invite foreign universities to set up
their branches in India how do you see
this decision will it affect our
educational centers
so um yes I I heard about this I'm not
sure what rules and regulations are
going to be uh imposed on these foreign
universities which would be desirous of
opening uh their branches in India
so uh until we know that we know that we
don't until so right now we don't know
that so what's what do I what do how do
I see this so I think this could be a
double-edged sword on the one hand if
foreign universities are allowed to open
branches in India then lots of Indians
who go abroad for those foreign degrees
may not have to do that anymore yeah the
lots of Indian city Indian youngsters uh
they go abroad because Indian the Indian
education system we know is is not up to
the Mark it's it's not where it should
be and that's why it is they feel it's
better to get a foreign degree so now
you could get a Yale degree Harbor
degree Oxford degree whatever else
degree in India itself so the the
expenditure will go down drastically
obviously these universities I'm sure
will be kind of expensive but it won't
be anywhere as expensive as having to
you know go abroad and you may not get a
scholarship there and it's extremely
expensive you know like
oh 20 30 lakhs a year or something like
that that's what I hear yeah so you
won't have to pay that much so in in
that sense it's good for those who wish
those who want to who feel the need to
go outside of India to get a degree
they'll be able to get in India itself
secondly it could it will certainly give
a great amount of competition to India's
archaic
uh academic institutions universities
Etc it'll give a great deal of
competition to them uh it will also be
good for people who are seeking jobs as
teachers and you know professors or
whatever they will get uh good options
you know they could all it will be good
for them also on their CV that I I
taught at so-and-so University and
obviously uh so the best
uh fresh Talent may be recruited in
these foreign universities so it is good
for them those who are seeking jobs and
all that and it also overall uh increase
the quality of Education yep so I'm
talking about the positives right now so
it will give I I think a much needed
needed wake-up call to the Indian
universities who have had no comp no
competition who have had a captive
audience and who have the worst of
Standards you know we have some
institutions in India the top level
institutions like the which which are
which may may be considered to be world
class we have really good professors and
and scientists Etc in some of them in
the Institute of science iits there are
lots of problems in the iits as well
I've spoken about that but overall it's
gonna but if you look at the other
universities in India the standards are
nothing to be proud of and I'm sure we
all know that yeah so it's gonna be it's
gonna give a tremendous amount of
competition to those universities that
have been doing nothing all these years
yeah and it's going to be a wake-up call
for them so it's now going to be survive
or sink or swim that sort of thing
hopefully yeah these are the positives
now obviously we will have to regulate
what these universities these foreign
universities they teach in India we
don't them we don't want them teaching
uh critical race Theory and try to to
Morpher into critical caste Theory or
whatever they'll try to do that we
should decide what we want them to teach
and what we don't want them to teach
ideally I would like to see them offer
education in the hard sciences and in
engineering and Technology I don't want
to see Humanities and all those fake
subjects history of course is not a fake
subject sociology also can be a
wonderful uh
free love of study and research yeah but
the way it's being taught these days is
horrific it's terrible and please
understand there are no there's no such
thing as a social science a social
science is a misnomer it's not a science
these are not Sciences so we were I
would say that the government needs to
be very clear about what it would like
with what it would like what value it
would like these universities to bring
to India and what we don't want these
universities to do we don't want them to
to to you know try to fragment Indian
Society more and teach the work culture
which is now Rife in the west yeah
so that is a big danger we don't want
any of that I if I were in charge of
this of course I'm not I'm just saying
hypothetically if I ever in charge of
this I would say only science is hard
Sciences engineering and Technology we
want that we want those skills we want
that knowledge we want that high level
of Education in the hard Sciences in
technology in education yeah
not in the social sciences we don't need
that so that's what I would do yeah
that's that's how uh as far as I would
go I would not want them to start
teaching anything they like there needs
to be very a clear set of guidelines and
not guidelines but preconditions
so I think it's it's a it's a
double-edged sword like I said there are
Pros there are cons there are positive
significant positives it's gonna finally
hopefully wake up the Indian
universities or maybe make them
irrelevant
that would be great
because these universities Indian
universities these professors who have
jobs for Life 99 I would say that 95 of
the professors are useless
five percent I am sure of are wonderful
we know some of them yesterday I had
Professor Desi Raju on my podcast what a
brilliant man he is what a fascinating
book is written it's over here yeah so
we have Brilliant Minds in India no
doubt about it but that's the two
percent
that's a two percent in maybe in a place
like the iisc Indian Institute of
science there may be most of them will
be brilliant yeah but in most
universities our professors are ah 95 of
them are mediocre
to be kind to them yeah most of them are
absolutely useless we know that
so uh these new universities could if
they end up making the Indian
the existing Legacy in Indian
institutions uh universities irrelevant
then it may be a good thing yeah so
maybe this could be a way of revamping
our education system over the next 10 20
years and we need that we do need that
and we need the right kind of thinking
and all that you know scientific
approach uh
so we would like the science there's not
any of the other nonsense that these
universities are known to bring and
maybe we should also decide what sort of
uh ratio we want of the professors uh
maybe like in the IPL in in an 11 member
team I think how many foreigners are
allowed three four I'm not sure two uh
so we need to have that sort of ratio
also in the university in the stuff you
know
so maybe 80 soft would be Indian 20
foreign
maybe derive some inspiration from the
IPA and various uh sporting leagues yeah
you you have to think creatively and
obviously logically as well yeah so yeah
it's I think it's an interesting
experiment and if we do it well it could
really end up revolutionizing our
education system obviously the education
policy also has to change and I'm not
sure about the whole reservations thing
if you bring reservations into this then
what's the point of doing anything at
all
so yeah that's where it is we still we
still don't have sufficient Clarity but
I I think it's a promising thing if you
do it right all right
all right
samarth says are India China and Russia
fighting against each other for
influence in Central Asia interestingly
all have bases in Tajikistan yes now we
know yeah uh should India improve its
ties with the russian-led csto Nations
uh what's the full form of that we'll
see uh especially in defense cooperation
to keep an eye on China the quad focuses
more on the india-pacific indo-pacific
region Russia needs India against the
against both the U.S and China so okay
let's look at Central Asia the map
where's the map there is never an
episode of any of my live streams
without the map on the screen we read
the map
to orient ourselves here is the map now
we are staring at the Indian Ocean
wonderful let's go to Central Asia which
is uh essentially the old uttara mudra
region which once belonged to our people
yeah once maybe in the future we'll see
okay this is Central Asia which
essentially is north of Afghanistan up
to Afghanistan it's part of the Indian
subcontinent and culturally it's not
Central Asian then you have even
Tajikistan is actually not turkic
Tajikistan is an ironic indo-ironic
Nation yeah most of the people but if
you look at the xinjiang region which is
currently occupied by China then if you
look at Kyrgyzstan Kazakhstan
um and all these nations it's all
Central Asia
some people like to include Northern
Afghanistan into that as well I don't
but whatever okay so the question is is
are India China Russia fighting each
other for influence so first of all let
us disabuse ourselves of the notion that
India has much influence in Central Asia
you only have influence if you have a
direct land access to this place yeah
and our land access to Central Asia has
been cut off since 1947 1948. thanks to
the British and thanks to our wonderful
leaders who did nothing to change the
status quo whatever was imposed on India
so India has no land access to Central
Asia if we take back pojk then we will
uh once again regain access to
Afghanistan our historical access to
Afghanistan maybe we should take a
little bit more than pojk you know
because the wakan corridor is a very
mountainous region if you want to build
roads it's really really hard to build
highways and Railways in the wakan
corridor so we need essentially more
than the wakan corridor more than pojk
we need a little more maybe the northern
slice of of the temporary artificial
nation of Pakistan and all that yeah
so if we get if we regain land access
that has been uh denied to us for the
past 80 or so years then we will start
having an influence in in Central Asia
we'll be start first of all we will be
able to start helping out the Afghans
more substantially than we are right now
and so on
so right now India has we could say
minimal or insignificant influence
direct influence in Central Asia
obviously all the Central Asian nations
are favorably predisposed towards India
because India is a non hegemonic
non-threatening Nation yes nobody fears
India which in a sense is a good thing
because everyone's open to cooperate
of course it's also a bad thing but
that's a different story
so um and and as you say there are all
three nations have bases in in
Tajikistan now first understand this
when it comes to Central Asia the former
uh Soviet Republic
today Russia regards these this entire
region these former Soviet republics as
part of their strategic extended
strategic neighborhood they will not
tolerate any other Nation encroaching
into their strategic sphere of influence
strategic zone of influence they regard
these nations as the Russians regard
these nations as their exclusive
zone of strategic influence all right
that's how it is and they conduct the
Russians conduct military exercises with
almost all nations on a regular ongoing
basis to to maintain those ties and to
ensure that these nations remember who
who is the uh who is who is essentially
the boss that's that's how it is so uh
so now if India has two air bases in
Tajikistan or one or whatever it is we
have gone through that yeah there is any
air base in the farcor air base aini is
definitely operational farcor maybe not
not so much
so if India has air bases in Tajikistan
it is only because the Russians have
allowed it that is how we have to
understand this had the Russians been
not open to this it would not have
happened the tajiks would have said no
thank you India we are not in a position
to allow you to open an air base here so
because Russia has acquised to this
Arrangement that's why it's happened
and the Chinese also have
a military base in the in the region of
Tajikistan the Palmer region which the
Chinese considered to be disputed they
have a military base close to the Afghan
vacant corridor
so the Chinese are are eyeing the bakan
corridor for a variety of reasons they
always have this expansionist mindset
so now I'm not sure how much uh the
Russians how happy the Russians are
about the Chinese uh military base in
Tajikistan but maybe the Russians also
need to you know mollify pacify China
and keep China on their side and you
know there's hard negotiations that
happen and the Chinese must have
extracted this pound of Flesh
so um so it's it's good for India that
we have these two footholds in Central
Asia we have very ancient relationships
with the region that's a whole different
story but uh
influence apart from that is very less
the air bases in Tajikistan that India
has are only because the projects are
happy to have that yeah so we obviously
uh have a good relationship with the
projects apart from that we see if you
do you if you want to let's say let's
say I want to go to Bishkek in
Kyrgyzstan you know most Indians don't
even know what Kyrgyzstan is Right north
of of Jammu and Kashmir you you go to
ladakh you go to pangong or whatever
it's just I mean it's it's
geographically kind of a stone throwback
the nation of Kyrgyzstan and Indians
don't know don't even know about it if
you want to take a flight to bishek here
to go through Dubai or Abu dhabios or
whatever there are no direct flights as
far as I know between India and Bishkek
or India and dushanbe you have to go why
you know you would take a circuitous
route so the people-to-people
relationship is kind of non-existent
there are no direct flights between
these nations India and these nations so
uh it's something that India can work on
so the influence that India has
is quite kind of less
um so it's it's basically right now more
like Russia versus China kind of game
that's being played and I'm sure the
Russians would like Indian support in
this obviously in India would be
definitely willing to support Russia in
whatever uh
geostrategic Endeavors they have in the
region we don't want the Chinese to
encroach in this region and become more
influential than whatever little they
are right now the Chinese obviously have
this Bri thing which they would like to
revive the past three years it's been
dead the built-in Road initiative then
all of that goes through Central Asia
they already have some rail Rail lines
and all that that go all the way to
Europe
so it's right now a game of Russia
versus China if India is able to manage
to
change the geographical status in
Northern India
then India could become a player in
Central Asia yeah but until we do that
it's just um it's all you know
it's it's uh India's influence is
minimal and essentially non-existent we
have good diplomatic relations with them
we have very friendly diplomatic
relations with these nations yeah but
apart from that there's nothing we are
doing if you want to have real influence
you will start building roads that
connect India to that region you will
start building railway lines that
connect India to that region you to
start having daily flights between India
maybe from Delhi or Mumbai to let's say
dushanbe or or ashkabat or or almati or
Bishkek or all that um
then you will have some influence and
that influence is typically
constructed through infrastructure and
Supply chains and supply routes we don't
have that right now
your influence is not created through
words
geopolitical geostrategic influence
comes is is is an outcome of creating
infrastructure and India is currently
not in a position to create
infrastructure so for India to start
having an influence again after almost a
century in Central Asia we will have to
reconfigure the geography of Northern
India which is something that actually
needs to be done on a priority basis
yeah we need to find a way one way or
the other of of retaking poke uh taking
some more territory out of the the
artificial nation of Pakistan
connecting once again reconnecting with
with our brothers and sisters in
Afghanistan yeah and through Afghanistan
we can uh move into Central Asia with
obviously with the ascent of the Afghan
government and all that which I'm sure
they'll be happy to so that is the deal
uh should India improve its size with
the other CST of Nations yeah we should
improve ties with all these nations
let's start with having daily flights
between India and these nations yeah uh
you know Central Asia is a wonderful
place beautiful place good culture uh
beautiful scenery mountains lakes
valleys
um you look at Tajikistan it kind of
reminds you of ladakh yeah so very very
beautiful landscape and all that so it's
a great place for tourism you open that
up for Indians Indians will be happy to
go there Indians nowadays uh go to so
many different nations for tourism why
not Central Asia which is in our
backyard
so why can't India start daily flights
between maybe Delhi or Mumbai and the
various capitals of the Central Asian
Nations why can't we do that why are we
so
um you know not taking these obvious
steps so that's something we could do
and we can obviously uh start exporting
weapons and all that to these nations if
if they want or find other creative ways
of if of
improving our cooperation and
coordination with these nations
so yeah that's uh what I say should
happen but the main thing is
we need to reconfigure the geography of
Northern India and make it
more favorable for us that's something
that needs to happen on a priority basis
yes
how can we stop the foreign fundings for
anti-india activities do you think our
government is doing enough to prevent
these fundings I think the government is
very aware of what's Happening
I'm sure it's monitoring the bank
accounts of all the anti-india
organizations that exist within India we
know that they all most of them get
foreign funding yeah funding from abroad
now I'm not going to specify the names
of any organizations I think we all know
roughly what they are yeah I am sure
the Indian government is keeping a very
close eye on it now the question is why
doesn't India stop all this because
there is foreign geography geopolitical
pressure most of this funding comes from
the West some of it from may come from
other places
the other places from which the funding
comes we have certain we have good
relationships we have developed good
close relationships of late with those
other places when it comes to the West
the West is antagonistic to India they
want they would like nothing to than to
see India balkanized
and how what better way to balkanize
India than create Fishers and divisions
within India and for that you use well
religion and other things in and we know
what what the deal is I don't want to go
into specifics yeah and for that you
need money and then money comes in the
form of US dollars
billions of US dollars are poured into
these activities into the uh bank
accounts of various organizations in
India every year billions of dollars for
various such activities that all fall
under freedom of expression freedom of
religion freedom of speech and human
rights and all that yeah right now the
the world order the so-called
rules-based World Order is entirely
dominated by the West which is the US
and you cannot do certain things Beyond
a certain point right now yeah so they
are able to influence the internal
affairs of India also less than the
influence the internal affairs of other
nations but it's still there and certain
things it is maybe not the right time to
do it we need to First Rise a little bit
more so how do we stop the foreign
funding this is the question
the foreign fundings once again I repeat
come in the form of U.S dollars you know
foreign Nation like India
to let's say India wants to India has a
certain amount of Foreign Exchange
reserves yes I don't know what the
quantity is right now but let's say
India wants to acquire an extra 100
billion dollars in terms of U.S dollars
in foreign exchange reserves what does
India have to do for that India has to
trade and earn that extra 100 billion
dollars if China wants to increase its
its foreign exchange reserves by a
hundred billion dollars they have to
trade and earn that money
it's a lot of effort yeah if the U.S
wants to earn 100 billion dollars what
do they do they print it
they print the money
either real money or digitally
that money is controlled by them they
can create new money out of thin air
anytime they want
that is the unfair Advantage the U.S has
and that's why they can keep on pushing
any amount of money into India for
anti-india activities do you understand
this
that is the true strength and power that
they have so
right now
there is a concerted
move in a certain direction
geographically uh geopolitically
nations are looking for alternatives to
the US dollar there is
talk of a brics currency India is now
the Indian rupee is now accepted in
certain Nations as as a foreign you know
as a currency for foreign trade in Sri
Lanka in other nations as well the
Indian upis is getting uh
it is being adopted in various Nations
so the in in many nations are now
willing to trade willing to purchase oil
using Indian rupees the Russians are are
uh they are willing to take Indian
rupees in exchange for oil yeah so the
Indian rupees uh standing has grown
strength has grown similarly the Chinese
Yuan the Russian Ruble have all
strengthened yeah you may see the
various currency exchange rates and all
in you will see it's not doing well and
all look at the big picture day on if
you look at the fluctuations of
currencies on a day-to-day basis or a
month-to-one basis you will not see the
real picture the big picture is that the
non-dollar currencies like the rupee
the ruble and and the Yuan especially
maybe even the real are now becoming
significant alternatives to the US
dollar not yet not yet it could happen
especially if you if they could combine
some their
um their strengths and create a basket
currency like like the like the brics
currency which is being proposed if
something like that happens it's going
to be a big blow to the US
dollar and to the euro the euro is
essentially you know controlled by the
US
so the moment this happens and there is
an alternative for the world and it's a
real viable alternative a currency that
is backed by a basket of of genuine
Commodities not promises and debt then
the world will be more inclined possibly
to start using that currency if that
currency is a proxy for gold if the
currency is is based on a genuine basket
of commodities
and then the US dollar even if they keep
printing it it may it will become you
know if if there's a genuine alternative
available then the US dollar will lose
that strength that it has and then it
will be difficult for these foreign
powers Western powers to fund these
anti-india activities so the amount at
least that they are doing right now yeah
so we have to strengthen our currency we
have to strengthen our economy we have
to maybe join forces with certain other
nations and create an alternative system
you do that then the current system will
become weakened there is a global desire
it looks like for you know moving away
from the US dollar we haven't people
have had enough of of the US dollar and
the hegemony of The Americans
so if that happens then the strength the
power of the US dollar will will become
significantly weakened I won't say that
it will evaporate overnight if it
evaporates then the antenna activities
will cease they will stop
yep
because most of it is is being done
through the US dollar I would say almost
all of it so that is the thing so for
these anti-india activities to stop
Indian is to get stronger the Indian
economy needs to cross five trillion
dollars and then 10 trillion dollars of
an annual GDP that's number one we need
to get stronger once that happens we
will be you know in a stronger position
to negotiate diplomatically and you know
to safeguard our interests a weak nation
is open to all kinds of external
interference a strong Nation can push
back so India needs to get stronger and
stronger and stronger that's what needs
to happen I understand people are not
happy that the government is not doing
this or doing that but we the government
sees things and knows things that you we
are not able to see
I can guess at what those things are I
don't know what I don't have the
specific details but I I understand how
this how the world works
so we have to understand that there are
lots of things out there that are that
we are not able to see it's all lying in
plain sight the more you study the more
you analyze the more visible it becomes
but that's how it is so the funding is
all in terms of is all through the US
dollar as the US dollar weakens the
funding will also weaken yeah so India
needs to rise India needs to get
stronger that's a deal
Anish says well thank you Anish thank
you the question is uh please tell us
more about the alternative origin story
featuring dios dios pitru and prithvi
Mata especially since it's directly
related to Zeus and Jupiter and even the
no even the Norse deities sadly most of
what is there of this ancient story is
totally Pro AIT AMT okay
so uh so
and the prithvi Mata these are the the
you could say the in in the rigveda
there are mentions of of these deities
these divinities and they the OSH petro
and Petri Mata are essentially the
parents of all the other gods yeah
whether it is Agni whether it is uh
who whichever other rig Vedic deities
you have the entire Pantheon of gods of
Hindu gods and goddesses their parents
are
pitru and prithvi Mata the sky father
and Earth mother that's how it is Surya
is also
a sun The Offspring of the Ash pitra and
prithvi Mata so these are the old Prima
primordial
parent
god and goddess in the rigveda older
than the old oldest yeah even uh when it
comes to Indra that the parentage is
kind of
there's there's a lack of clarity on the
parentage
in some verses he is referred to Indra
as as the twin of Agni the twin brother
of Agni and Agni we know is is a child
of the hospital so by that sense Indra
would be the son of the ocean
and uh and so on so Indra is referred to
as the king of the Gods yeah the
greatest of the Gods the great warrior
and there are incredible there are so
many references to him in the Rigby the
more than any other God if I'm not
mistaken but the old the Primal the
primordial god and goddess or Josh pitra
and pratimata and you find parallels
with this in other religious systems as
well if you look at uh the old religion
of the turko Mongol people
uh tengirism it's called tengirism but
it's not an ism it's not an abrahamic
religion you know there are lots of
people who claim that tingrism is a
monotheistic
religion such nonsense
also there's a whole Pantheon of gods
and the two Primal the two primary
deities are dengri the sky father and
umai the Earth mother so once again you
have this parallel yeah it's a
polytheistic thing
now so uh Josh Peter and prithvi Mata
are the two parents of all the other
gods in the rigvedic pantheon which
eventually became the pantheon of all
the indo-europe in the same of the
entire Euro Indo-European culture which
spread across Eurasia westwards out of
India yeah uh there is no alternative
origin story this is the story this is
the thing you can look up the rigvedic
text and all that it's all there there
are even English translations available
online I will not look it up now and put
it on the screen I'm sure you can do
that much of homework if you are so
interested
so um now when it comes to Zeus and
Jupiter so those spit through became
Zeus Peter
and Zeus Peter became Jupiter that's how
it went even Western encyclopedias and
all that will tell you that so so the
Greek God Zeus Peter is clearly
the same it's a copy it's a replica of
the older
Vedic God Joe
becomes Zeus Peter but in the case of
Zeus Zeus Peter he also has incorporated
elements of the great God Indra
so it
so it's look like it looks like they
have combined elements of two deities in
one
in all the Western gods that are modeled
after Lord Indra Zeus is modeled after
Lord Indra his primary weapon is a
thunderbolt which is indra's primary
weapon the vajra and Indra has two
vajiras one is the Thunderbolt and one
is the the hammer which is also called
the vajira the Tibetan vajra and all you
know these are Hammer shaped objects
that are supposed to be holy so that is
the the club the mace or the hammer so
Indra had two vajiras one is the
Thunderbolt and one is the club or the
hammer
so uh Zeus also has a thunderbolt and he
also is supposed to be a hammer God
Jupiter is nothing is nothing but the
Roman version of Zeus so Jupiter is also
a Thunder God and all that and then you
have the Nordic deity uh the pantheon of
deities whose primary great God is Thor
who is nothing but the same as Zeus and
Jupiter and parjanya and all that uh
um a combination of these of these
deities you know so uh and when it comes
to Zeus and Jupiter and Thor they very
clearly have the same story as Indra
Indra is the oldest of them all so Indra
in the rigveda is mentioned as having
defeated and killed a Great Serpent a
great eye the old Sanskrit word for
snake or serpent is Ahi Ahi so there was
this great he called
who had encircled the oceans of the
world all the Waters of the world and
this has caught this had caused a great
drought and everybody would die because
the Victor has done this had done this
so Indra went ahead and fought this
Great Serpent vitra and defeated him and
he was able to liberate the oceans of
the world and water was once again
available to to All Humans so that was
one of indra's great heroic Deeds so in
the story of Zeus he also battles a
great sea serpent and defeats him in the
story of Jupiter obviously the same
story in the story of Thor Thor defeats
a great sea monster called yormungandra
and it's the same story all over again
so uh they are all modeled after uh
after Indra actually and they also uh
have Incorporated some elements of the
old of the oldest God that we know of
which is Josh pitro because Zeus Peter
is named after the hospital but he
incorporates elements of Indra so I
think what happened is that there were
multiple migrations out of India at some
point in time
in the aftermath of the battle of the
Ten Kings which is mentioned which is
mentioned in the rig Veda itself and
many other later uh migrations also and
these migrants they went so far out of
India that they kind of lost touch with
their ancestral culture but they
continued in it in some form in certain
stories got combined together certain
divinities got combined together and
that's how we had the rise of of uh
composite deities like Zeus Peter who is
a an amalgam of Yosh pitru and and Indra
and then that a copy of that was Jupiter
because the Romans they they absorbed
gods of everybody they defeated they
defeated the Greeks the Romans and the
Greeks are actually very very similar
people more or less the same people at
that point in time two thousand years
ago and and Greece is right almost right
next to to Rome you know across the
ionians see the agency all that I didn't
see
um
so yeah so then they they absorb the
Greek god and they started calling him
Jupiter or maybe they had done it before
I don't know exactly what the chronology
is but they are the same Divinity Zeus
and Jupiter so that is the deal the
north deities are nothing but uh the
Norse representation of the old rig
Vedic Pantheon the Greek pantheon of
gods with some exceptions are all is
also a replica of the of the rig Vedic
The Vedic Pantheon of gods obviously
some gods are are unique that that may
have sprung out of the imagination of
the Greeks some Roman gods may have
sprung out of the imagination of the
Romans but the overall structure of the
pantheon is essentially more or less
identical
as the old the oldest the origin the
original Pantheon which is
that's the deal that yeah I I would
invite you all I would encourage you all
to go ahead and read the rigveda for an
understanding of of the ocean there are
several verses that refer to this these
divinities if you look at an if you if
you read an English translation the
problem is that you will not see any
reference of divyosh pitra
in English translations he is referred
to as the sky father of the heavenly
father
they don't use the term for him they use
the term Sky father or heavenly father
or something like that
so yeah you you have to ideally you
should read the Sanskrit version or a
translation into your native language
maybe whatever Indian native language is
is your mother tongue that would be a
more accurate translation I would say
but yeah go ahead and read it if you are
interested in this it's a very
fascinating topic
um
rajit says should the Indian government
spend money on bullet trains or the one
day Bharat Express or should India the
in government improve our local trains
first what's your opinions on this
so you know um life is not a zero
zero-sum game it's not a question of
either this or that only one thing we
should do first it's not like that it's
uh you know we we get those questions
all the time this question all the time
India has so much poverty and so much
all that so why is India developing a
space program why are you developing
rockets and futuristic technology when
you have so many problems well they did
not ask the same question to the to the
to the to the Russians Russia was
devastated in the aftermath of World War
II you have no idea of the devastation
Russia suffered
did the Russians went ahead with the
space program
why why did nobody ask the question the
same question to the Russians yeah the
Chinese
until the 1990s were extremely poor
Nation but they've had a space program
since the 1960s and 1970s with the help
of the Russians yeah
so
the thing is that you have to develop
everything in parallel you can't
prioritize only one thing I will only do
this first and only when I perfect this
will I go for something else that's not
how it works you have to India is a
nation of 1.3 billion people India is
you know the per capita GDP is still not
where it should be but India is no
longer a weak poor Nation as a as a
nation we are actually powerful and we
are rich the government has access to
incredible amounts of money
yes so we need to work on these things
together at the same time in parallel
we need to have start building a bullet
train Network we need to start building
a high-speed rail network like the Vande
Bharat expresses and in the meanwhile we
should also start working on improving
the quality of local trains and
eventually we want to replace those
local trades also with much faster
trains it's all something you need to do
in parallel not one after the other in
sequels no not like that okay so what
the government is doing is exactly the
right thing let people criticize and
yeah the the purpose of all this
criticism through the media and various
other people is to influence the minds
of the ordinary people and make them
feel like the government is doing
something wrong and the government is
using our money for the wrong purposes
that's not the case we need a high-speed
rail network ideally we should have
bullet trains everywhere bullet trains
are expensive so we go for Pandey Park
trains also the most important routes
will be covered should be covered first
with the bullet trains eventually in the
next 50 years maybe all trains should be
bullet trained maybe yeah 50 years
so right now the Mumbai
I think right now they're constructing a
Mumbai Ahmedabad link yeah bullet print
link eventually we should connect that
with Delhi maybe Mumbai to Bangalore
bangaluru Mumbai to Chennai Chennai to
Kolkata whatever the main cities you
know let's say the top 10 cities those
should be interconnected eventually
first through bullet trains the other
routes should be improved slowly
gradually
and local trains also slowly should
improve them but maybe that the the aim
should be that in the next 50 years most
of this should be replaced by bullet
trains next 50 years it's not too much
to think of it that way 50 years
so that's the kind of thinking we need
to have so it's not like we need to
priorize only prioritize only one thing
first and only when you perfect that
will you go to the next step no do
everything in parallel that's how you
will develop lots of different kinds of
capabilities at the same time that's
what needs to happen
all right
Sharma is big yes sir Sharma is big uh
the Chinese have a deity called The
Monkey King which is their version of
Lord Hanuman how did they come to start
revering him did Lord Hanuman ever visit
China
and how else influenced them look Lord
Hanuman
clearly was a historical figure the
ramayana is a historical event this
happened before the Mahabharata and they
could tentatively date the ramayan to I
don't know several thousand years before
today we know that there are mentions of
the river Saraswati in the ramayan in
the Saraswati is
a great powerful River in the time of
the ramayan it's depicted like that it's
not depicted as a river that's drying
out yeah and the river started drying
out after 6000 BC this is 8 000 years
before today and it dried out mostly uh
by about 1500 BC that's three and a half
thousand years before today so the
ramayan would have happened closer to 8
000 BC than to 1500 BC that's how I see
it there will be people who disagree and
people who have all these dates I am not
going into that controversy none that's
not not my concern right now so the
ramayan most likely happened closer to
8000 BC was there any China in 8 000 BC
simple question China is about 3000
years old Chinese civilization is about
three thousand three and a half thousand
years old if you want to be nice to them
yeah that's it
and why would Lord Hanuman ever visit
China I mean there is no evidence of him
having done that and China did not even
exist as a culture in a civilization at
the time of the ramayana therefore there
is no connection that way
between Lord Hanuman and China
all right now the question is uh the The
Monkey King right uh what do the Chinese
call The Monkey King they have novels in
which he is a he's a major character
let's
I think he is called the Sun Wukong or
something let's Google this
let us Google it right
uh
so the so the Chinese have
all right one second
so the Chinese have this this deity
which is very clearly
a
influenced by Lord Chinese
Monkey King
Kong I believe it's called soon
[Music]
okay let's go to Wikipedia as always let
me uh remind you that Wikipedia is not
always not necessarily a reliable source
of information especially when it comes
to Indian culture industry
but I'm just taking a cursory look at
this so The Monkey King yes Sun Wukong
and Mandarin Chinese is a legendary
mythical figure uh best known as the
main characteristic of the 16th century
Chinese no Journey to the West yes
Journey to the West is a novel that
essentially is the story of of the
Chinese Pilgrim schwanzang who traveled
to India
and it's the story of his travels and
the the the adventures he had the
hardships the hardships he faced while
traveling across the mountains in
Central Asia and all that and uh
schwanzang essentially came to India to
gain knowledge to gain great Indian
knowledge the various Buddhist sutras
and other sutras that he took back to
China translated into Chinese from
Sanskrit and all that
um the Chinese obviously we know they
called India
um chanju the center of Heaven they
consider themselves to be the center of
Earth the Middle Kingdom but they
considered India to be the center of
Heaven
and India's influence on China is is at
least 2 000 years old at least uh and
it's all been a one-way traffic of
cultural influences India has absorbed
no Chinese culture at all in the past
2000 years but China has absorbed
incredible humongous amounts of of
Indian culture yeah uh so one of these
is is so in this novel what is it called
Journey to the West Sun Wukong The
Monkey King is one of the main
characters who helps schwanzang in in
his journey to India and uh I so what
does it say the monkey has certain
Supernatural Powers because of Taoist
practices and uh
amazing strength and he's the king of
all the other monkeys and things like
that yeah and uh there is speculation
over here somewhere I believe that uh
yeah the ramayana right The Monkey King
was possibly influenced by the Hindu
deity ramayan the monkey god the Hindu
Hanuman the monkey god from ramayan it's
not possibly it's definitely there is no
other monkey god in the world no other
Monkey King in the world the original
one is anuman the Chinese have had 2 000
years of Indian influence so obviously
this this and obviously even the Chinese
are a polytheistic uh culture some
Chinese I believe they they uh they
revered certain monkeys yeah this they
considered certain monkeys the Gibbons
or whatever to be uh divinities or
something you know there is so there
have been some elements of of uh
revering monkeys as gods or divinities
even in Chinese culture it's been there
but the character of The Monkey King
Bears so much resemblance the character
of Sun Wukong Bears so much resemblance
to Hanuman that it can be no other
uh so so that's what it is so The Monkey
King the Sun Wukong is essentially a
Chinese
uh representation
of Lord Hanuman it's it's inspired from
Lord Hanuman and uh yeah it's it's uh
one of the divinities in Chinese culture
and religion Dharma has influenced the
Chinese immensely
uh mostly via Buddhism Buddhism is part
of sanatan Dharma by the way and I'm
sure that people will come and say no
blah blah blah I don't care it is what
it is you may like to disagree it's your
choice but uh so the Chinese and it's
not just Buddhist divinities that you
see in China you see all the various
Hindu difficulties also in China there
have been Hindu temples in China
in the Chinese transmitted the same
culture or eastwards to Japan and in
Japan you have every single Hindu god
and goddess gods and goddesses that are
classified today as Hindu gods and
goddesses not Buddhist gods and
goddesses you know uh benzathin in Japan
is is Saraswati and then Lakshmi is
there uh Lord mahakal is there Lord
Shiva is there which is the same thing
you know what I mean yeah so it's had in
an immense amount of influence on China
on Eastern Asia on Japan on Korea and
Southeast Asia it's a whole different
story so yeah it's been there right
om says can India use the G20 Summit to
promote tourism and change India's image
worldwide so those are two different
things and there is some overlap tourism
and changing India's image worldwide
there is some overlap between these two
things so
so I am participating in this in the s20
component of the G20 thing at this month
end the the inaugural meeting of the s20
event it's in pondicherry pudicherry
and uh one of the days is entirely
devoted to tourism because tourism is an
integral
is has been made an integral part of all
these events of all the G20 events that
are going to be held in India this year
I think it's a G20 policy yeah so
tourism is going to be an integral part
of this so one so if the meeting is two
days or three days one day is entirely
devoted to traveling around the local
place which will be producer in my case
this month end and all the foreign
delegates will get to see or whatever
the the puducherry has to offer you know
uh the local sites and attractions uh
the local culture the local Cuisine and
all that and there are going to be
events all across India in north in the
northeast of India in uh in Bhopal in
lakshadweep in in all the parts of India
in in ladakh in jamun Kashmir as well
yeah lots and lots of events over the
entire year of India's presidency and
tourism is going to be an integral part
of that so it's definitely going to give
an enormous amount of exposure uh of
two foreign delegates
to India yeah so they're going to get a
great amount of exposure to Indian
culture to Indian history Indian
architecture and all these things
which is good for India uh now how do we
change India's image worldwide we have
to put us best foot forward in whatever
meetings uh or whatever events are being
organized in India we have to showcase
our strengths our achievements our
talent uh the wonderful young people
that we have what what uh abilities they
have what potential they have you know
what we have achieved what we are
working on various Indian Institutes of
whatever whether it is in the in the
field of culture whether it's in the
field of science whether it's in
administration whether it's in
governance uh whether it's in science
and technology whether it's in Industry
we have to Showcase all of this and
that's what the government is going to
do yes uh so we need to put our best
step uh foot forward and uh
clearly we are we the government has
appointed the right leaders in in all
the various things and that's what we're
going to do so it's going to be a great
opportunity this entire year to Showcase
what our achievements are what our
beautiful nation is like
yeah what our potential is what our
capabilities are and it's it's it's a
great opportunity for us to use this
year to get to become even better you
know raise our standards like I keep
saying so yeah the G20 Summit is
definitely going to uh
be something that will do all these
things yeah
swapnil says can you explain explain the
concept of first principles thinking in
science and philosophy and how can we
apply it in our day-to-day life well I'm
not sure about philosophy I mean I'm no
expert in philosophy I'm not a
philosopher as as far as I know
the concept of first principle thinking
first principles thinking is something
that I
understand is from science as far as I
know yeah first principle thinking
foundational principles thinking it's
about a certain kind of thinking process
it's about a certain kind of process of
reasoning
how do you construct your reasoning most
of us we we reason or we think about
things in a very specific
narrow manner yeah
we we have this dogmatic dogmatic kind
of thinking people there is a certain
accepted version of the truth and we
just believe it we don't ever question
it yeah first principles thinking is
about questioning everything
questioning everything at all so for
instance let me give you a few examples
let me give you an example from science
for instance why do crystals let's talk
about science first then I will give you
examples of other things as well so in
science you have crystals you know
crystals quartz crystals diamonds we all
know what a diamond looks like I guess
yeah so the question is why are diamonds
the way they are or why are crystals the
way they are why do they have these
specific shapes why do why did they
always come in a certain kind of shape
quartz crystals always take a certain
kind of shape diamonds always come in a
certain chemistry why is it that way why
do they have these properties so then
you ask yourself why why is it like this
why is this angle there or this thing
and all so then you will start realizing
so then you have to think from a
foundational perspective from the
foundational uh principles of physics
so what laws of physics apply to
crystals and then you will realize that
none of the Newtonian laws of physics
apply to crystals
then you will realize if you could dig
deeper into it that a crystal is a
macroscopic Quantum bound State it's a
purely Quantum object it's a giant
molecule that's what a crystal is and
its properties depend on on the on what
the crystal is made of so so in case of
diamond it's a tetrahedral carbon
Crystal yeah one carbon atom attached to
four different uh carbon atoms and all
that which gives us it this Incredible
strength uh hardness and all that
so that's how you think in terms of the
foundational principles the concepts of
physics the first principles of physics
and Mathematics now let's say let's
apply to something else let's say you
have a kid you have a kid and you tell
the kid okay beta it's it's nine o'clock
in the night let's go to sleep and the
kid will say why why should I go to
sleep you know kids are really good at
thinking from first principles because
they keep asking why why why why and
most parents will say no it's why
because I tell you so I said so that's
why that's not how it works so then you
you force the child to accept dogmatic
thinking instead of answering the
question of why
if a child asks you why should I sleep
at night you have to tell them that you
need to sleep at a certain time and wake
up at a certain time to have a healthy
circadian cycle the the body the brain
has something called a circadian cycle
and it needs to be maintained regularly
at a you know the sleep wake cycle so
the first thing when you wake up is that
you need to see the sun sunlight you
need to have sunlight on your skin maybe
indirectly in your eyes that that you
know transforms the the uh that gives
certain chemical signals to the brain
and then it gives you about 14 15 hours
of waking time and then you sleep again
you have to have a regular routine of
that so that's why you do sleep at nine
yeah or whatever time and because you're
a kid you need more sleep than adults
that's why you have to explain it
properly and also then the child will
say but what if I don't sleep why should
I sleep then you have to explain why
sleep is necessary
if you don't sleep then you're gonna be
your brain will not function properly
why will the brain not function properly
is the next question so you have to go
deeper and deeper into it and then break
it down to the first principle the
foundations yeah why do you need sleep
and that's that's a question that's not
really been answered in in in in
medicine
but that's how it is so you have to keep
asking why why why what exactly you to
start with the question of what exactly
do I think then you have to ask yourself
why do I think this and how do I know
this is true and what if this is not
true
yeah so keep asking why I think there's
this principle of asking why five times
why why why why why you ask a question
why you get an answer then you ask why
that then you get a different answer
then you ask why that then you get a
different answer and it's a
it's all you can apply this to to
business you can apply this to to
engineering you can apply this to
history I always keep talking about
causality in the causal chain it's not
enough to study history from the
perspective of memorizing dates because
that tells you nothing you have to think
of history as a causal chain why did
this happen why did chingas can't refuse
to invade India
yes that is an example of first
principles thinking it's the video with
the most views on this channel
that's where I applied first principles
thinking Genghis Khan did not leave
behind a diary or a memoir or a record
which in which he explains his behavior
he has left behind nothing so we only
have the data of what he did in his life
and then we have to apply first
principles of human psychology and and
and and and
the laws of power and geostrategy and
try to figure out why he did something
why why why
so that's how I was able to deconstruct
why he refused to invade India because
you don't you go through his entire life
history all the decisions he took to
understand the thinking patterns and the
behavioral patterns he had the decision
making patterns he had then you
understand what his motivations are what
his psychology is and then you can
understand then you use that and apply
it to he his decision of the question
that he had should I invade or not and
when you understand the pattern and the
thought process of the psychology then
you will understand why he did not
invade India it's all about first
principles thinking you think this way
you will have a much better chance at
success
in the various Endeavors you are in life
if you think of if you if you have the
different thought parts of the dogmatic
thinking that you just think what
everybody else wants you to think the
accepted wisdom then there will ever
never be any human progress for instance
when I was a kid not when I was a kid
when I was in college and all I always
used to eat an ice cream when I had a
cough or a cold now this goes against
all accepted wisdom we know that if you
go to a if you are someone who's
accustomed to living in a warm place
and you go to a cold place let's say you
go to ladakh in Winter where right now
it will be minus 10 degrees in Lay or
something minus 10 minus 15 degrees
nose running and all are indeed Co
caused by very cold weather weather
atmospheric conditions yes and of course
the altitude is also there but it
doesn't mean that it's caused by eating
cold things
and it also doesn't mean that if you eat
cold things it's going to make your
cough or cold worse yeah if it was so
then the people who live in cold places
they would have a miserable life every
time they had a cough or a cold but it's
not the case yeah so I always found I
always I tried this out I'm an
experimenter in some some things yeah
um I like to question things because of
the first principles thinking which I
think it's not something because of my
scientific training it's something that
I've always had so whenever I had a cuff
or a cold I would eat an ice cream you
know and see if it makes things work
worse it never made anything worse maybe
it's only specific to Me Maybe for some
other people it makes things worse and
of course if you believe that if you do
something it's gonna make your life
worse it will happen
yeah so it's about that but if you so
it's it's about being uh doing things
that are against accepted wisdom only
after you think it through properly
you could call it scientific thinking
you could call it first principles
thinking foundational principles
thinking whatever it is it's all about
questioning it's all about being clear
clearly analyzing things what do I think
why do I think this how do I know it is
true how do I know this is not true what
if I did this and what happens and you
try to break it down to the first
principles the foundational principles
and that's how it is so I think Elon
Musk has spoken about this that's why
it's become very famous these days what
is first principles thinking and all
that yeah so that's the deal
that's what I could offer you in in
brief
Daniel Nicholson says okay let's apply
first principles thinking to this
Daniel Nicholson says why are Andhra
Pradesh and odisha so prone to cyclonic
storms how would the global climatic
climate change
climate how would the global climatic
change affect the increased decrease in
Cyclone frequency in our Eastern
Seaboard let us
put the map on the screen because we are
talking about yeah
here's the map where's the map here's
the map
so and it's not only about the east
coast of India see some of the most
terrible cyclonic storms uh have in the
past have occurred in Bangladesh in
Bengal so it's the entire eastern coast
of India even Tamil Nadu Etc even even
Sri Lanka
typically it's the eastern coast of
India that wears the brunt of these
regular
cyclonic storms that occur in the in the
sea of Kalinga yeah
and it's not only there you will see
that there is something called a
hurricane season in the U.S it's always
on the East Coast it's typically on the
East Coast mostly often in the Gulf of
Mexico yeah typically the southern state
of the U.S are hit repeatedly every year
in and that's how it is so so
the question is then you have to apply
first principles thinking I'm doing this
in real time now yeah I've not thought
this through
you have something called the atmosphere
on our planet the planet has a magnetic
field the planet rotates around its own
axis it goes around the Sun it not in a
circular orbit but in an elliptical
orbit and the axis of the rotation is
tilted it's not sprayed with respect to
the plane of the elliptic uh the the
plane of the solar system so you have
seasons on the planet because of this
tilt of the axis so the at any given
point in time either the other either
either the Northern Hemisphere or the
southern hemisphere is hotter and
obviously the the side of the earth that
is facing the Sun at any given point in
time is going to be warmer because of
these differences in temperature you
have currents in the atmosphere and
currents in the oceans of the world in
the oceans there are currents you know
in Japan you have the Japanese current
which is called the Kuroshio current
in the Atlantic you have What's called
the Gulf Stream that also impacts that
also passes through passes uh impact or
affects uh
Britain the United Kingdom yeah see the
UK
is at the same latitude as as
Newfoundland where you have polar bears
Newfoundland is incredibly cold we have
polar bears there the UK is at the same
latitude but it's much warmer why is
that
why is that it's because of the Gulf
Stream the ocean current which is a warm
current in the cold Atlantic so because
of the various uh
phenomena that are caused by the Earth's
Tilt by the seasons by the day and night
boundary and all that and by the
rotation of the Earth around the Sun we
have these various
oh
of atmospheric and meteorological
phenomena on our planet so uh there is
something called the equator where the
temperature remains more or less the
same there's a lot of rain there and
there are these various ocean currents
and there are various what they call
Trade Winds
and this Trade Winds they change
direction every six months or so yeah
uh so these winds also they the the
reverse Direction and all and in India
we have the monsoon season which is also
a periodic thing it's a seasonal thing
yeah so all weather on a large if you
look at whether from a day-to-day basis
the change of weather on day to day
basis you will get confused but if you
look at look at it from a year to your
your perspective you will see these
patterns of weather there's recurring
patterns that you see in weather in
climate all across the planet and you
can actually kind of predict that if you
have the right amount of data so on the
basis of all these things you have
certain phenomena which also depend on
geography yep
so over here in Indonesia we have these
islands that lie on the equator and
there are these tremendous tropical
storms that happen all the time south of
India there are no Islands so the
weather over here along the Equator is
very different the climate in in the
weather is very different along the
Indonesian Islands then let's see in the
Maldives where the islands are very
insignificant very small so the weather
in Indonesia is very different
from that of the Maldives and this
region Indonesia Etc it's quite close to
the Sea of Kalinga so-called Bay of
Bengal and maybe so I'm saying maybe
okay I don't know the answers because
I'm just thinking of about this from
first principles so you have the warm
air down here
and you have cooler air here and you
have the the monsoon and you have the
tropical climate seasonal climate so
maybe it is the interaction of the
Indian Monsoon the the uh moisture Laden
clouds
and and the cooler temperatures they
bring along with the hotter air and the
in the air currents of the uh equatorial
region that lead to these churning
cyclonic storms that are spawned in the
Indian Monsoon repeatedly there's at
least one cyclonic storm every year
typically in the monsoon season but also
at other other times also sometimes yeah
and a similar process most likely
happens in uh the Eastern Atlantic
Seaboard of the U.S where you have this
repeated hurricanes that that hammer
that that are the east coast of the U.S
multiple times every year that's also
seasonal so all weather on a macroscopic
scale large scale is seasonal and you
can predict that this these few months a
certain kind of weather is going to be
visible so it's because of these so
these cyclonic storms that uh that
batter the eastern coast of India that
that this phenomenon is because of the
cyclic nature of the atmosphere of the
weather and it all the the first the
foundational principles and the reasons
the the root cause of that is the tilt
of the Earth's rotational axis with
respect to the
um the uh plane of the solar system is
because because of the day night uh
boundary so one side is cooler one side
is hotter and also because of the
seasons
so all of that causes weather and
whether that is cyclical in nature and
that's why you have a storm season a
cyclone season in eastern India and a
hurricane season in the U.S and there
will be such other patterns in all parts
of the world there is the El Nino and el
Nino's uh you know uh phenomena also
that happened in a in a cyclical manner
every few years and you have the Indian
Monsoon which also is a yearly
phenomenon so that's the first
principles thinking that you can apply
to this question
I want to ask you three questions
okay let's take one I'll take one
question let's take the first question
what's the first question if a living
organism is also ultimately made of
atoms and all non-living things are also
made of atoms like this
like these books everything else then
what exactly makes a living being living
what exactly is life then yes everything
is made of atoms yeah we are made of
atoms the metal here is made of atoms
the word the books which is all that
this thing here is everything is atoms
my clothes all atoms yeah
so the question you're asking is what
exactly differentiates life living
organisms from from non-living material
non-living substances so there are
several characteristics that are common
to all living organisms firstly they're
made of cells you take a microscope and
you take let's say
blood sample or whatever you go you put
in a slide you mount it in the
microscope put the light on and you go
deep into it you will see cells red
blood cells white blood cells other
cells cells
human tissue is made of cells there are
fat cells there are muscle cells and all
kinds of other cells right skin cells
and there are specialized cells and so
on so all living organisms are made of
cells those cells obviously are made up
of proteins and other things and and
deep inside you have atoms yeah so atoms
are at the foundation of everything in
in the the four percent Universal we we
see yeah uh these atoms they create they
give rise to molecules these molecules
give rise to various chemicals chemical
substances the chemical substances are
what make are us are what make up life
the carbon chemistry that that we are we
are carbon creatures our carbon based
life forms so all living beings are made
up of cells you will not find any living
being that doesn't have a cell yeah so
cells are the basic unit of life now all
living beings have either DNA or RNA
take viruses you have RNA viruses you
have DNA viruses
the most infamous RNA virus of these
days is you know what
you know what so uh all living beings
are made of cells all living beings have
DNA or RNA living beings can grow and
develop they can reproduce and pass on
their genetic information
to their offspring
non-living beings non-living materials
can't do this yeah and uh
living beings can regulate their
internal environment we human beings all
have a certain
temperature in 98 Point whatever degrees
Fahrenheit
yeah you go about that it's a fever and
things are not well so
in your normal healthy State you are
able to regulate your internal
temperature and all the internal
subsystems systems and subsystems that
make up your body and this is something
that applies to all living beings they
can regulate their internal environment
then they respond to external stimuli
and living beings evolve like I said
they can pass on their genetic
information to their offspring and you
this happens about Generations
generation of a generation and
eventually there are there is evolution
living beings evolve and there is
natural selection survival of the
fittest in the environment right so
that's the deal these are some of the
the characteristics of living beings now
when I spoke I spoke about viruses
viruses are curious creatures
they are kind of on the boundary between
living and non-living living and dead
yeah so they don't regulate their
internal environment they can't do that
and viruses don't even respond to
stimuli mostly they don't respond to
stimuli yeah but they do have DNA or RNA
they do have a cell membrane a cell
structure they do reproduce and pass on
genetic information to their offspring
and they do evolve they do mutate and
evolve we know they evolve enough
so yeah viruses are they're like
crystals in a sense you know
they of course have proteins and all
that yep and they have DNA already so
viruses are on the dividing boundary
kind of between living and non-living
but this the fact that they have DNA or
RNA in my opinion makes them living
beings yeah so these are the
characteristics of living organisms we
are living organisms our dog our cat our
bird pets whatever
and whatever else we see trees all
living organisms they all share these
characteristics even plants respond to
external stimuli maybe not in the sense
that we do but they do
you see uh if you see uh what they what
they call it um
what do they call it
that video in which you speed time up
I I forgot the term you see those videos
in which the time is speeded up and you
see uh the the behavior of a plant in
let's say 60 seconds that what it does
in three days then you will see that it
responds to stimuli you put a light on
it's going to turn in the direction to
get more light and so that it can
enhance the photosynthesis in the night
time the leaves they droop down on the
clothes and that sort of thing if you if
you see a time lapse a time lapse of a
forest from above you will see that the
trees the shift their positions multiple
times in a day and they all try to stay
away from their neighbors and keep some
space in between so even plants respond
to their external environments and all
that so that's essentially the
difference between living and non-living
even though everything is made up of
atoms all right
um Daniel lincolnson says do elephants
have Superior intelligence compared to
other animals given the size of size
sizes of their heads vis-a-vis the
thorax and abdomen
could elephants eventually evolve into a
civilized species like humans if we
don't intervene from outside are we a
civilized species
uh uh okay you mean okay I know what I
know what you're asking yeah so uh
elephants they have enormous heads yeah
let's talk about not head size but brain
size
so the human brain I think on average is
about 1.3 1.2 1.314 1.4 kilos let's say
1.3 kilos the average weight of the
human brain when it comes to the
elephant the average weight I believe is
5 kilos
almost four
four times the size of a human brain
roughly so elevens have massive enormous
brains compared to humans if you if you
compare that with the gorilla excuse me
gorillas they have brains that are
roughly half a kilo in in weight
our chimpanzees chimpanzee cousins who
are
gorillas and chimpanzees are very
closely related to us gorillas are one
are half a kilo chimpanzees are about
0.4 kilos 400 grams the brain quite
small
when it comes to dolphins aquatic
creatures dolphins have slightly larger
brains than humans 1.6 kilos I think
the dolphin when it comes to Orcas the
killer whales which don't ever hurt
humans
their brains weigh about seven kilos
even larger than elephants yeah and the
sperm whale it has the largest brain
that we know of it's about nine kilos
nine kilos
that's enormous and you see all these
species they are very highly intelligent
now they may not be intelligent in the
same way as us but they are highly
social they are we we know that they are
playful they when it comes to let's say
orcas you know the killer whales we know
that they cooperate in Hunts they pass
on Hunting techniques complex and
sophisticated hunting techniques to
their children they train them
repeatedly
it's like a training course of a few
weeks on how to how to you know perfect
a certain Cooperative hunting technique
very sophisticated ending techniques so
orcas are highly intelligent they
communicate they are known to
communicate with human being so can
dolphins sperm whales also they have
enormous brains and they are very
intelligent they have very social uh
lives very complex social lives when it
comes to elephants elephants are
incredibly intelligent
um they are they I don't know they
clearly have emotions
They Mourn their dead they revisit the
the the place where their ancestors died
year after year after year for decades
they have very long lasting memories
yeah elephants are very intelligent they
also have strong emotions elephants
believe me elephants have strong
emotions
emotions like compassion emotions like
lung love emotions like anger good God
elephants can get angry you know and the
same thing you will see in our primate
relatives the gorillas and the
chimpanzees so I don't know if elephants
have Superior intelligence compared to
some other creatures maybe they do
definitely an elephant would have a
superior intelligence compared to let's
see a squirrel
that's what it looks like
um
and you know when it comes to Evolution
whether they evolve into let's say
civilized species I I think in some ways
elephants are very civilized already
um so
so will they evolve into a different
kind of species evolution is a constant
never-ending process but it doesn't
happen over a course of weeks or months
it takes
typically hundreds of thousands of years
for evolution to to change the way a
species appears and behaves uh
the oldest evidence that we have of
anatomically modern humans Homo sapiens
uh is found in uh was found in a cave in
North Africa I believe in Algeria
uh so these specimens of homo sapiens
fossils are about 300 000 years old
three lakh years old they are
anatomically like us but there are
certain differences yeah like the the
brow is much heavier you know much
larger if you see so if you see
chimpanzees or gorillas they've got very
big brows over here a big Ridge over
here
homo sapiens have slightly slightly
larger brow brow bones or whatever it is
you know the brow Ridge and all so there
are certain differences that you find in
the humans that were alive three lakh
years before today and yet they were
anatomically more or less just like us
they were Homo sapiens the same species
is us
so homo sapiens has not evolved much in
three lakh years
and if you look at the history of
humanity overall
um
uh the the human chimpanzee split
happened about two million years before
today
so that that's how that's like
um
there is like uh 20 lakh years you know
in terms of lacks and crores
so typically it takes about half a
million years about five lakh years for
significant evolutionary changes to
become visible apparent so if you give
if you wait for another five lakh years
I'm sure elephants will look different
they may have evolved in a different way
so evolution is something that is
essentially about adaptation long term
to environmental changes and obviously
you want to keep on increasing your
chances of survival in whatever changing
environment you live in and that's
something that takes a lot of time like
I said hundreds of thousands of years So
eventually elephants will will evolve
into something else
and in the past if we only have to look
at the past history of elephants you
know elephants in if you look at the
Deep ancestry of elephants then their
ancestors maybe like several tens of
millions of years ago where dog-like
creatures if you look at the ancestors
of whales whales you know the ancestors
of whales were dog or bear like
creatures that lived on on land and then
over
millions of years they adapted to start
living in in in in oceans
so this is a process that takes a very
long time minimum half a million years
typically tens of millions of years So
eventually elephants will evolve into
something else eventually we will
involve evolve into something else if we
hang around that long yeah we have been
around for a very long time humans
our ancestors survived the the chip
impact event of 66 million years ago
which killed off the non-avian Dinosaurs
the avian dinosaurs are still around I
see them every day
so yeah okay
samartha Gandhi says do dogs understand
human language to some extent and how do
dogs process television
uh dogs do understand human language uh
certain dogs be dog breeds not species
certain dog breeds are very intelligent
the Indian dog is a very intelligent uh
breed of dogs yeah it's one of the
oldest breed of dogs maybe maybe the
oldest breed of dogs it's the Indian
so-called Pariah dog yeah
so dogs are very intelligent as we know
they are their Man's Best Friend human
beings best friend and they do
understand human language they don't
understand all the nuances and all that
the details but they understand the
basic conversation if two people are
talking if you have a dog who is a pet
in his he or she has grown up with you
then you and your family members talk
they will understand most of it
they will not understand deeply
philosophical topics or complicated
things like that politics and
geopolitics and and things like that but
regular basic conversation let's go
shopping let's go to the park what shall
we eat shall we eat this I'm angry I'm
happy all that stuff they will
understand you tell your dog okay go out
of the window you go to the door and sit
outside for five minutes
they may not understand they may not
understand what five minutes means but
they will certainly go and sit outside
and they'll do what what you tell them
to do if they are
well if they so if they are so inclined
so dogs understand more than we believe
they do they understand human language
you will see dogs throwing tantrums and
arguing and I don't want this I want
that all that cats also understand a lot
but of course cats that's pretty not to
understand anything cats also understand
a lot but cats are a very different kind
of creature they're also
they're the two big the two major pets
that we have the species that we are the
most closely allied with are dogs and
cats and they're very different yeah so
cats also actually understand human
language but they pretend not to they
pretend not to pay attention because
that's how they are that's what cats do
we own dogs but cats own us that's how
it is now how do dogs process television
in the past you had those cathode ray
tube televisions those box TVs right
um in the Box TV you have an electron
gun that that you know paints a picture
on the screen line by line and it it
happens that I don't know how many
frames per second 24 frames per second
or whatever it's a line by line thing
yeah so I think I believe dogs could not
see that even cats could not see the
problem they would only see the line
coming out but today we have LCD LED LCD
whatever it is the technology that is
something dogs and cats can see just as
well as us because you will see dogs
watching TV you even see Cats watching
TV and watching movies and reacting to
things you know when there's a horror
movie they'll react they'll show fear
and they'll run off whatever so they
when it comes to the new technology that
we have the the LED or LCD LED I believe
the dogs and cats can see it just as
well as us yeah the same thing they see
color differently from us
and uh and they see certain
certain frequencies of light Spectra or
certain certain wavelength of light that
we can't see so maybe that is something
that's missing in in the LED uh images
that we use for our convenience so they
may find the image to be kind of weird
from their perspective because it
doesn't show uh things in those
wavelengths possibly but uh it is well
known that dogs and cats are known to
watch TV and actually get engrossed in
things so that's how it is yeah
foreign
says did the Chinese teach manipuris how
to make bricks is may they make a
combination of lie and me language see
Maite is not a language it is a script
yes it is the script that is used to
write the methi the manipuri language uh
in the past because of historical events
uh the manipuri language was written in
the Bengali script
so you go back to people who studied in
school 30 years ago they would be more
familiar and more comfortable with the
Bengali script you go to Manipur today
all the kids they learn they are taught
to write and read in the news in the
actually the original script the
mathematic script which has been
reconstructed of late
uh so methi make is a script it is not a
language now the manipuri language is
classified as a tibeto Burman language
which means it is it is uh it has
characteristics that are similar to the
Tibetan language and also it has
Burmese language so that's a whole
spectrum of languages let's put the map
on the screen map
uh yeah map because money was here in
the Far East of India south of nagaland
north of mizoram east of Myanmar West of
meghalaya in Assam yeah
um
best of West of Assam silchar Etc is
very close actually to imphal you know
and all that yeah so uh there's a whole
uh bunch of languages
which are the tibeto Burman languages
which are spoken in Burma in the Far
East of in the so-called Northeast of
India and in Tibet and Tibet is
classified as a cyanotibetan language
why why does Sino have to come in there
but whatever they don't have the
linguists they have made a whole mess of
the entire science of linguistics
Linguistics should have been a science
they've turned it into a joke
uh it was a science in the days of
uh of acharya Panini yeah he is the
father of linguistics at that time it
was a science now it's a joke so anyhow
so uh but it is indeed true that money
the methi language Manipur language has
characteristics of
of Tibetan for instance in in the
Tibetan language
a place is called la like Shangri-La we
know Shangri-La means place in manipuri
also La Means A Place
for instance kangla a dry place that
sort of thing so um
language I'm not sure what if what if
any connection it has with the lie in
the me language right now about the
Chinese teaching Manipur is how to make
bricks so that uh
I believe it comes from the the story of
kagemba
there was a manipuri King let's put that
on the screen now
uh
let's go here
okay I'm going to read Wikipedia once
again don't ever trust Wikipedia I'm
just putting it for reference there was
a manipuri king called khagamba he was
called the Conqueror of the Chinese I
believe he would have conquered some
territory in in Yunnan uh which some
people would say is part of China
currently it's part of China so he
conquered some territory in Yunnan and
uh
he is called the Conqueror of China he
ruled between 1597 and 1654. uh let's
put a map on the screen so Manipur as
you see is is over here yeah
this is the Burmese Kingdom the Ming
Dynasty at that time
it it appears was uh
it had a boundary with the kingdom of
Manipur and it looks and and we know
that uh
did conquer some territory that was part
of the Chinese Ming Empire at the time
so he's called the Conqueror of the
Chinese and he brought back certain
several prisoners of War into Manipur
and if the story goes
but these Chinese prisoners of War
taught the manipuris how to make bricks
which I think is quite laughable
yeah
why do I say this okay let's go back to
the map I I say this for a certain
precise reason
let's go to the map once again
and I'll show you why why I say this so
you go to Manipur the the major city in
the valley region is in Fall the capital
of Manipur you go into fall you zoom in
there is a place called the kangla fort
which is essentially the the the heart
of Manipur that's where Manipur is a
culture as a civilization is said to
have ever emerged the kangla fort yeah
there is a gate over here there's a moat
around the place there is the kangla
Fort and then there are there is the
uh there is a govindaji temple inside
and there is also an archaeological site
where more archaeological exp work is
being done I don't remember remember
where it is
somewhere around here there are
excavations happening inside the kangla
port I believe the ASI would be involved
um there are significant portions of the
kangla fort that still remain
underground that are not excavated they
have not been researched at all some of
the excavation work is still going on if
you go there you will see that some of
it is underground some of it is
overground some of it is half exposed to
the Sun and so on when you go and look
into it you will find bricks
the kangla fort is around 2000 years old
at least maybe older than that
so there were bricks all right in the
kangla fort I think if you're in Manipur
you can go and see it for yourself
so this entire story of the Chinese
teaching Manipur is how to make bricks
are you kidding me I don't know how such
story is coming to the popular
imagination but yeah it's it's a myth
it's nonsense
all right
says okay four questions let's take the
first question I always take the first
question what's your favorite Samurai of
all time
my favorite Samurai of all time there
were lots of great Samurai leaders
and so on if you want me to pick one I
would pick the great Miyamoto
Musashi Miyamoto Musashi so Musashi was
a great Samurai great swordsman he was a
he was he wrote this great book the book
of five rings I would recommend you all
read this no people talk about uh The
Art of War which was written by Sun Tzu
well I would say you should read the
book of five rings which is written by
Miyamoto Musashi yep the book is mainly
about
swordsmanship yeah how to wield a sword
so Musashi was uh Samurai who were the
Samurais they were the Japanese warrior
class
you could call them the chatras of Japan
yeah
very very strict principles very strict
regimented life
um they ruled Japan more or less for
close to A Thousand Years yeah
um they had this way of life called
Bushido the way of the warrior yeah and
the Miyamoto Musashi was one of the
great Samurai and a great writer he
wrote This Book of five rings it's about
swordsmanship it's about martial arts
but it's also it's also about life it's
also a book about life through
swordsmanship and martial arts it's
divided into like it says book of five
rings it's about it's divided into five
sections earth water fire wind and the
void the void so I will not go into what
the book is about what the details are
but if you want me to name my favorite
I would say Miyamoto Musashi and I would
recommend if you are so inclined do read
his book The Book of five rings great
book
knowledge Seeker says what would be the
mindset of the great leaders when they
lost or it seemed like they would lose
let me quote Miyamoto Musashi
to win any battle you must fight as if
you are already dead
which means you must commit fully to the
cause and a leader a great leader would
be fully committed to the cause whatever
the causes and in any Leader's life in
any person's life there will be times
when you are close to failure and you
may even fail we talk about Genghis Khan
he never lost a single military campaign
but he lost several battles
and at times things would have looked
Bleak for him but he always found a way
to
to come out to to succeed at the end it
doesn't matter if you lose a couple of
battles here and there but you must win
the military campaign you you you
participate in the World Cup for Cricket
or football it's okay to lose a match or
two but the overall game the goal has to
be achieved so the mindset is you never
give up
first of all a great leader it doesn't
become a great leader just by not giving
up there are other qualities that a
great leader must have if you have those
qualities you never give up it's do or
die you are fully committed and to win a
battle you must fight as if you have
already dead which means you have
nothing to lose if I die if I lose it's
fine I don't care but I'm gonna do my
best in leadership like like I've said
in the past is service you don't a
leader is not a selfish person you don't
fight for yourself you don't have
ulterior motives you don't have
conflicts of interest you are fully
committed to one cause that is the cause
of serving your nation your people
whatever it is whoever you're leading
you cannot lead the whole world you have
to have a specific limited constituency
of people whom you lead yeah so that's
how it is
leadership is about service and to win
any battle you must fight as if you are
already dead and a leader who is
completely committed
will will say it's okay we're gonna no
matter what happens we're gonna keep on
going we're gonna fight till then and
obviously that's how it goes so that's
the mindset of great dealers lots of
great leaders have come close to failure
some have even failed but then emerged
again and then one that's how it goes
sarkar says
who are you who are your favorite
fictional detectives mine are feluda by
satyajit Rai Roy
and the Sherlock Holmes by Arthur Conan
Doyle uh
yeah I have indeed read Sherlock Holmes
I've seen some of the the series The Old
series and all that our great detective
great great fictional detective maybe
the greatest fictional detective of all
time Sherlock Holmes you asked me I will
give you strange names uh
I don't have one single favorite
fictional detector the names that come
to mind
are for instance Thompson and Thompson
Thompson and Thompson the two detectives
from the Tintin uh Comics yeah
that's one I can think of some names you
may not know of David Addison from
Moonlighting portrayed by Bruce Willis
yeah Remington Steele ported by Pierce
Brosnan
uh inspector cluzo
portrayed by Peter Sellers in the Pink
Panther series later on he was portrayed
by Steve Martin which I did not enjoy at
all yeah so these are some of my
favorite fictional detectives yes
[Music]
um
you said pediflya says human beings
revert back to their primordial Savage
animalistic form like misogyny sexism
violence killing tribalism debauchery
and unspeakable Horrors why do it why
does it happen why why do humans revert
to this well first of all
we are indeed animals there is something
that sets us aside from animals which is
culture and civilization but sometimes
culture and civilization breaks down in
some societies there is no for for
whatever reason there is war or whatever
there is no rule of law and order and
you are forced to to to fight with your
fellow human beings for for mere
survival for food and all that's when
you are left with no choice then that
should never happen but unfortunately in
the world it happens so that's one
reason yeah in in some societies the
culture itself is like that I am not
naming anybody please please okay let's
not get into controversies I'm not
naming any society in certain societies
the culture is such that certain things
are allowed
yeah in the past it may have been like
that today also there may be some places
possibly somewhere
yep so it's like that
but
as long as you have a set of moral and
ethical
uh values
and you are consistent to those values
and principles you're gonna live like a
civilized human being and not like an
animal when those things break down you
go back to being an animal yeah and of
course some people are incapable of
being an animal even if they don't even
if they are living in the wild
uh and some people are naturally
predisposed to violence and all that so
in every society you have some criminal
elements and all that's how it is but
overall is from a societal perspective
when a society is under great stress
when there is let's say foreign
occupation that's where your culture uh
is no longer something you can control
and you know there are external cultural
impositions on you and those that taint
becomes part of your culture and if you
that's one possibility and if you are a
nation at War and there are no resources
available because of warfare then you
may be you may be forced to fight for
very small things like just food or
water and in support your family and the
only way to do that is to fight your
fellow human beings that is horrible
that also happens yeah
so um that's how it is and of course
there is greed you know Nations fight
each other sometimes for territory look
at Chinese expansionism so on so
typically this uh reverting to
animalistic behavior is because of
uh breakdown of culture and civilization
when those that set of values and morals
and ethics goes away that's when some
human beings can revert to such Behavior
which is unfortunate yes
let's take one more question Sharma is
Big says could you please interview the
girl could you please tell me the girl
that played Jenny in RR and at the end
could you tell her that if she ever
finds herself in Melbourne Melbourne
Australia I laksha Sharma would can show
her around for free I'd highly
appreciate this who's the girl who
played that thing let's shall we Google
it here let's Google who who's the girl
that played the the role of Jenny Jenny
this is there was a Jenny in Forrest
Gump wasn't there but this is a
different Journey
so let's go to this incognito tab let's
go to imdb.com imdb.com boom
oh and let's search for RR RR
this movie and let's see who that a lady
is what is her name uh I think this is
the one you have Jennifer right Jenny
her name is Olivia Morris Olivia Morris
she is from England I believe she's
English
uh let's let's see if one can trace her
social media or something she has
Instagram yeah
let's see is there any email available
this is a
okay she she has a this photograph with
this wonderful gentleman here uh all
right that's an Instagram she also has a
Twitter yes so okay her name is not
Jenny her name is Olivia Morris
and so on
so listen I don't have anything in
common with this lady Olivia Morris I'm
not sure if I shall interview her I um I
I typically don't interview actors and
actresses uh
but you know what if she's watching by
any chance or if somebody who knows her
is watching please let the lady know her
name is Olivia Morris please please let
her know that there is this fine young
gentleman called laksha Sharma who will
be happy if he ever finds herself in
Melbourne to show her around for free so
uh please uh if she's watching please
please if Olivia you're watching please
know that if somebody who knows her is
watching please convey to her if she's
ever in Melbourne she can meet Mr
lakshama will be happy to show her
around free yes
all right uh I let's take some a live
chat questions for a few seconds yes uh
sorry I
what is that what is that
excuse me there's not stalking I'm doing
some genuine research on on
because of a request I'm not stalking
anyone please
uh all right
all right uh so what shall we see
somebody saying I'm simply excuse me I
don't simp
uh okay you have any questions you can
ask me
some questions
uh
do you move your hand while reading
to know the style of learning so I'm
reading and I'm moving my hand
I don't know okay some people they put
their finger on the text they are
reading in this they read line but I
don't do that I think I I absorb
entire paragraphs at once I don't know
how I read it I've never tried to
analyze it
um
I think I read
paragraph by paragraph not not word by
word I read really really fast I think
it's a kind of somewhat unusual this
period at which I read
[Music]
um
um what else
how's the book children of memory I
haven't started it yet I book I buy more
books than I can read and I have read
more books than I than I have bought I
have I
the book children of memory is a sequel
I believe to a previous book which I
have read in it which is brilliant and
that's why I bought the book children of
memory and there's a book called
children of Ruin as well
the first one is a book about spiders in
humans the second one I haven't read the
third one I haven't read but the first
one is brilliant yeah
absolutely brilliant
science fiction of course
all right let's take some other
questions uh
I'm always having out of body dreams why
is this happening I'm scared to sleep
please help someone I think you should
see a psychologist or psychiatrist or
something you know they can analyze
dreams they will ask you questions
they'll ask you about how you're feeling
and how and and how do you feel about
these out of body dreams what do you see
in these out of body dreams do you go
somewhere are you flying do you meet do
you meet some people who are terrifying
do you meet some supernatural beings how
do you feel about that what is your
reaction to that so you if you if it is
really a problem for you I don't think
I'm the right person to uh person to ask
you should actually see a psychiatrist
and and work through the issues that
maybe the root the root cause Behind
These Dreams uh dreams always I believe
have some connections with real life
and they typically tell you something
and they indicate some some something
about the the state of mind that you are
currently in or whatever circumstances
you're going through Sometimes some
people have a recurring dream it may
recur every night or it may recur
infrequently like once a year or
something but when it comes back you're
like oh wow this came back that sort of
thing and some people uh never have the
same dream again some people always have
a similar kind of dream and some people
have things like out of body dreams and
all that so yeah if it is a problem if
it is scaring you if it is affecting
your life you need to see a professional
maybe a psychiatrist and go through the
entire process and they will help you
um
address what this is really about it's
typically about some issues that you're
facing in your actual life
have you ever experienced sleep
paralysis I have not
uh sleep paralysis is when you sleep and
you become paralyzed and you're awake
but you can't move and typically you
feel some kind of Supernatural presence
in in the room maybe some heavy weight
on your chest like some some some being
is sitting on your chest and it's a very
frightful experience that's what I've
heard I have personally never
experienced it
um some people experience it multiple
times in their life
I'm not sure if everybody experiences
experiences of this sort of thing but
yeah I personally haven't experienced it
but it is some it is a phenomenon that
is known to uh be reasonably common and
it's a phenomenon that's known to have
existed mostly like throughout human
history there are even paintings of of
this thing it's called a night terror or
something you know paintings by I
believe European artists about a night
terror a person is sleeping and there's
some some Demon or something sitting on
their chest and that sort of thing
so yeah I personally haven't experienced
this
okay
um quickest practical way for India to
reach 15 trillion dollar GDP focus on
the economy manufacturing manufacturing
manufacturing and Export export export
that's the quickest and practical way
it's easier said than done but it can
happen next 20 years give yourself 20
years to reach 30 15 trillion dollars
why not
um
uh what will be the future of Canada
according to you or why so many
these eye rolls
what's the fear of Canada according to
me recession or economic collapse see
Canada is a huge gigantic ginormous
empty country mostly Frozen it uh the
the true owners the custodian the two
owners of the land are the ones who are
the most marginalized the ones who have
been genocided the Native Americans
that's a whole different thing today you
have a fascist dictator running the
country Justin Trudeau miss you Trudeau
is running the country uh
I don't think anyone likes him but
they'll keep electing him which is kind
of weird which kind of raises some
questions anyway the future of Canada
Canada is a U.S visa State okay and the
future of Canada is intrinsically tied
to the future of the US
Canada of course has no natural threats
it is uh
it is uh protected on two sides just
like the US by the oceans the Atlantic
and the Pacific uh what industries does
Canada have
Lumber
logging mining
and that sort of thing what does Canada
produce I'm not sure what Canada
produces
um so yeah I'm not sure what the future
of calendar is Canada doesn't even have
a cohesive distinctive culture
yeah all we can say about the people of
Canada the Canadian culture is that it's
nicer than the than the Americans
if you make Americans nice people they
they're Canadians so Canadians are like
nicer but poorer Americans what future
does the Canada have I am not sure
um it all depends on the U.S Canada
doesn't have any any real threat the
only threat if there is any is the U.S
but why would the U.S you know invade
Canada or whatever what's the need for
to do that to do that the future of
Canada for my from my perspective is
like I don't really consider Canada to
be an important Nation from any
perspective apart from the fact that it
occupies a gigantic amount of territory
mostly empty in North America yeah
eventually eventually I don't know I
don't know so I don't see I don't see
Canada as an important country that
really matters yeah it is Rich all that
it has a vast amounts of Natural
Resources all that is there these are
some of the advantages but it doesn't
have its own culture there is no such
thing as a unifying culture or identity
of Canada
it's all white settlers and settlers
from other nations other parts of the
world so I don't know what the future is
maybe a hundred years down the line
there may not even be a Canada you know
there could be Quebec and Alberta and
Newfoundland and uh
and all that who knows maybe you will
have Resurgence of the Native American
nations which would be great yeah but
yeah it's an artificially cobbled up
nation in such Nations typically don't
last too long yeah from a
historical perspective if you if you
look at a century upon Century typically
such Nations come and go artificially
constructed Nations so you know
yeah that's what I feel about it
Karthik says I have experienced sleep
paralysis once it was terrifying that's
what I hear that's what I hear that that
is really terrifying I am fortunate I've
never experienced it but uh
uh so I believe that the person who
experiences sleep paralysis is typically
conscious in the sense that they are
awake
and they're aware of the fact that
they're they're paralyzed they're unable
to move and eventually the ability to
move comes back after a few minutes or
maybe half an hour or whatever I'm not
sure about the time period is but even
if it is a few minutes it's it it feels
like forever
I've read about this and it's uh yeah
it's really scary like you get this cold
sweat and you're really frightened like
there's something frightful in the room
but you can't see it maybe I'm not sure
if you can open your eyes
but yeah that's how it is yeah so yeah I
know it's it's quite terrifying it's a
terrifying phenomenon
uh Roma Bliss says I am from Mauritius
sorry to our good friends in il Maurice
okay who was winner for
brown was one of the greatest rocket
scientists of all time he grew up in
Germany he uh
participated in the Nazi uh war program
the the development of the V1 and V2
ballistic the V1 and the V2 Rockets one
was a cruise missile the first ever
cruise missile and the second one was
the first ever ballistic missile after
World War II ended he surrendered to the
Americans yeah and then he was
transported to the U.S and he
essentially set up
the American space flight program yeah
so the American space flight program the
father of it is far enough on down
he was the director of NASA he was
initially a prisoner in the U.S yeah and
uh he was has never been able to escape
the Nazi taint some people keep on
insisting on calling him a Nazi listen
if you are born in Germany at the time
and the only way to become a scientist
is by cooperating with your government
um I suppose that what you have to do
that's one perspective of looking at it
I'm not justifying anything I'm just
saying that's how it was perhaps for him
and some people say that he did use
slave labor Jewish slave labor or
whatever Roma slave labor perhaps I
don't know in
as part of the of the uh activities he
was doing while he was uh in Germany so
that's that's a taint that has always
stayed with him maybe it will always
stay with him he died he was responsible
for the U.S uh Space Program he was the
father he oversaw personally
uh America's moon landing program in the
1960s yeah the Saturn V rocket was
developed under his supervision and
guidance yeah so maybe the greatest
rocket scientist of all time yeah
and it is German rocket technology that
eventually made its way into the US like
I'm saying and also into the USSR yeah
uh the r something rocket is something
the Soviets developed using German
know-how in technology and scientists
rocket scientists and that that USSR
space flight program which was a
developed from the from the German
program that eventually some of the
technology was transferred to China and
that's how the Chinese program began so
it all goes back to the Germans and to
Werner Von Brown yeah so he was
possibly the greatest rocket scientist
of all time but yes
he was part of Nazi Germany and that is
something that will always stay with him
sadly
but a great great scientist
all right I think we will stop uh we
will end this session here wonderful
session thank you all for your questions
I can see lots of questions coming in
all over again but uh I'm gonna end it
here yeah otherwise we'll go on forever
I know I can do it all night and you
will stay on some of you will stay or
stay on at least yeah so all right uh
I'm gonna end it here thank you so much
for your questions participation
wonderful I'm glad to her to have
reached 150 and we'll keep on going so
until next time take care thank you and
I'll see you soon bye